[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Jeff dittle I'm
excited to invite Chris Patterson as our
guest on the show today for a
conversation about mass transit and
event-driven systems Chris is a software
architect and an open source leader with
over 30 years of experience in designing
developing and deploying Technology
Solutions he is the owner and consultant
of loosely coupled LLC a company that
provides technology Consulting and
developer support services for mass
transit an open- Source distributed
application framework forn net Chris is
the founder and primary maintainer of
mass transit which he has been leading
since 2007 he is passionate about
creating and contributing to open source
projects that enable Developers to build
message-based applications with ease and
reliability he regularly produces
software development related content on
YouTube sharing his knowledge and
expertise with the community Chris it's
a pleasure to have you welcome to the
show hey thanks what a good introduction
I mean you basically covered it all well
that's great that's my
job so let's Dive Right In I mentioned
at the top of the show something about
mass transit which basically before we
get into mass transit we have to answer
a different question which is what is a
message bus and why should anybody care
you know that's a conversation that
comes up and it's something that has
historically been a number of different
things you know if you go back to kind
of the early software or service
oriented architectures and the concept
of this Enterprise service bus was
floated around and it was a lot of
corporate middleware it was a lot of big
vendor type things it was you know
generally when people of an agile and
kind of modern software development mind
set hear things like Enterprise service
bus they think oh my gosh that's just
crazy old SOA stuff and you know that's
not something we want and you know a
message bus is probably just a different
way of saying that we want to build
distributed applications in a durable
and reliable way and typically we do
that using message-based
message Brokers so things like rabit mq
Azure service bus Amazon has sqs active
mq these are message Brokers that are
able to do durable reliable delivery of
messages asynchronously so with net you
know for what the past gez it has to be
eight years we've had async and await in
the task parallel library and people
have really adopted that and the whole
framework you know if you look at the
latest asp.net everything is async Task
everything is around doing things
asynchronously in parallel concurrently
and it's really made Donnet a highly
thread aware highly scalable framework
for building applications and you know
if you look at the benchmarks and you
look at the way they built things async
has become kind of a staple of modern
software development using net and
accompanyment that needs to go along
with that is it used to be in our
applications things would be somewhat
synchronous you know think about it as a
transaction script I need to parse the
request from the customer I need to
store that request in a database I need
to insert some rows into the reporting
table I need to insert some rows into
this thing you know things like SQL
triggers and all of these ways of trying
to build a synchronous processing into
it is essentially a start to- finish
transaction script is how applications
were built well now that we're
asynchronous we want to do things like
oh well I can go update those other
tables separately I can do those
asynchronously so I'm not slowing down
the user response you know I want to
provide a fast response to the user so
instead of following that kind of
transaction script programming model we
are able to use a message bus to produce
events that can then asynchronously run
and do those things for us you know so
when a synchronous process completes
such as adding a customer I could
produce an event via a message bus that
says hey a customer was added and then
the follow-on processes such as updating
the building system to creating an
account or validating an address or
sending a confirmation email ma or any
of those other things that happen when
you create a new customer are able to
run asynchronously by consuming those
events on a message bus so it it's a way
of having execution and the word I
commonly hear is Pub sub I want Pub sub
for my event so a message bus provides
that Pub sub framework so that you don't
have to know all of the consumers of
those events up front you know because
like in that transaction script if you
wanted to add another step you would
have to go modify that original script
and you know insert some more rows or do
whatever or call an HTTP API any of
those things whereas with a message bus
and by using events and pubsub I'm able
to have an additive architecture where I
can add new capabilities to the system
without touching any of the front-end
customer creation code that customer
creation code works as it does produces
that event on the message bus and then a
consumer is able to take that message
from the message bus because it fans out
it's publish subscribe and do additional
capabilities without having to work
through the entire system and add that
function in so that's in general what a
message bus is at least how they're used
today versus you know how some might
think of the Enterprise service bus of
yester year so that kind of makes me
think a little bit about the open closed
principle which is the idea that you
know at least at the class level classes
should be open for extension and closed
for modification it's sounds like this
kind of brings that up to the level of
the system architecture but are there
some risks or complications to that I
wonder if somebody might think well it
was really easy for me to just open My
Method and change it and extend my
system and now you're telling me I have
this distributed message system I have
to deal with how would you speak to some
concerns that somebody might have about
adding complexity with these different
moving parts that maybe they're not
familiar with that's definitely the
trade-off that teams have to think about
you know and it's one of the questions I
think one of the early statements made
on by one of the you know the Elders of
software development so to speak is
don't distribute if at all possible
don't distribute you know when you build
a distributed system now you have two
problems or eight problems or goes back
to Peter Deutch and the eight fallacies
have distributed computed and we'll put
a link in the show notes to the episode
where I interviewed Peter talking about
just that so yes yeah exactly it's you
know the complexity does go up when you
build a distributed system now again
since we're talking about a message bus
and you know you mentioned mass transit
at the beginning it isn't always that
complexity that needs to come in so it
is possible to do durable asynchronous
processing without introducing a huge
amount of complexity but to discuss you
know what's a task there let's talk
about some atoms that are part of you
know a message bus system you have
producers and you have consumers
producers are things that run they could
be action methods on controllers they
could be a database process or some sort
of command line script that runs loads
some data in a database and produces an
event they can be anything that happens
where there's a change in state and that
change in state needs to be notified AKA
produced as an event so that other parts
of the system can react and respond to
those changes of state I mean that's
event-driven architecture by Design
events happen and systems respond to
those events so that's producers with
consumers it's you know at least with
mass transit it's a thing that takes an
event a message a command an event any
type of message and does something with
it they're very similar to controller
actions they are a method called consume
that gets the event passed to it you
know it's the Hollywood principle don't
call us we'll call you you don't have to
worry about reading and pulling from a
file and parsing all that stuff the
framework sits on top of rabbit mq or
Azure service bus and delivers a nicely
wrapped message to your consumer in a
method that you can then do whatever you
want with you can call HTTP calls you
can update database Road you can produce
other events I mean any of the things
that you can do in code you would do
within that consumer are there any real
world analogies that you can think of
that help people understand what a
message bus does maybe it's correlated
to something people are familiar with in
the real world I mean the most basic
thing that I can think of is you know
you go to an
ATM and you take out
$80 now the ATM is not making a real-
time call call to your bank to see if
you have $80 wait what it's
not apparently not based on you know
something that happened on social media
a while back and a bunch of people
overdrew their accounts but believe it
or not as long as you meet a threshold
it will give you money and if it's too
much hey that's when the fees come on
and that's a profit opportunity so when
you make a withdrawal from that ATM it's
storing off the event or the transaction
record that you took $80 from this
account number and that is then produced
back to the backend system which then
adjudicates those at the next business
day and all of that stuff walks out and
it goes from pending to completed or
whatever happens and the reason for that
is just the scale of debit level
transactions across the network on any
given day I mean everybody Taps to pay
everybody does everything the ATM
network they all work very similarly
yeah it's a great analogy too because if
it's down you can still get cash at
least for a period of time and I think
that hearkens back to the example you
gave before of being able to extend so
what if I had to crack open the ATM code
in order to have it email the person who
withdrew the funds and then if I wanted
to introduce SMS now I have to crack
open the ATM code and introduce SMS and
now we want to do push notifications to
your banking app so we're going to
update the ATM code so have a feeling
that's okay that's a perfect example
because all those things that happen but
so when I said before you know how does
this avoid making things more
complicated but what I just said kind of
sounds complicated too so sounds like
there's tradeoffs here between which one
you should do when there is so so one of
the things about building a distributed
system is being able to f11 through the
debugger or F10 through the debugger
depending which ID you use these days is
is not there you can't just Trace
through like your code you can today and
the reality is you can't do that anyway
because the second you call an HTTP API
or call a stored procedure or a database
function chances are you're not tracing
into that anyway you're waiting while
something remote happens and then hope
all ends up well and comes back so with
a distributed system you can't really
Trace through that you know you could
have multiple processes running in
multiple debuggers and when you produce
a message here you could then trap the
message consumption through a breakpoint
in that other code and it is possible to
do and people have done it I tend not to
do it that way because I find it
extremely frustrating but it does
increase the complexity you can't just
step through the transaction script code
and see everything happen but is that
really the case of any system these days
I mean we're building systems that are
more complex having to interoperate with
other systems and we don't want the
30second call to the service provider to
block the checkout accepted screen on
our ordering site when we can defer that
you know if you look at Amazon if you
really think that they've checked your
credit by the time you hit by no it
doesn't work that way your order is
created and they get your intent to
purchase and the adjudication of that
purchase happens all in the back end
asynchronously yeah and there you go I
think that's a good place to land that
opening section which is we try to model
systems as if the world is synchronous
but what many of us have discovered is
that the world is not synchronous the
world is asynchronous and so the systems
we should design should reflect that
fact and they'll be easier to understand
100% totally agree so before we get too
much more into message buses and then
mass transit specifically I do want to
help listeners understand something that
I run into a lot which is what's the
difference between a message bus you
mentioned a few you mentioned us from
Amazon Azure service bus you mentioned
rapid mq there are others what
differentiates that from an event
streaming system like Kafka or Pulsar
which listeners might be familiar with
yeah it's a question I actually get a
lot because sometimes people say well we
already have Kafka can we use that and
while mass transit can consume and
produce events from Kafka we have to
think about the overall architecture of
what Kafka is Kafka is a highly
available partitioned log file anything
you write to it in case you know they
call it a message is just appended to a
log within a specific partition and it's
kept for whatever the retention period
is you know a lot of companies keep it
for a long time and if they're using you
know Cloud kofka providers it works out
great because they don't have to manage
it and they get an event stream that
they can replay across however many
times they want but that's what it's for
it's a log file that has a nice API that
lets you consume things from it and they
provide a lot of value added services on
top of that to do things like rollups
and you know looking at Key fields and
saying well I want the most recent
version of this partition key you know
and so things like that what
differentiates a message broker from say
kfco or Pulsar is message Brokers
there's a number of semantics that they
have to support things like message
locking you know we're dealing with cues
so we're pulling messages from the front
of the queue locking them processing
them and then removing them from that
que whereas in Kafka you're not really
removing things you know and the
distributed locking the scalability
comes from being able to have multiple
consumers on the same queue and have
them all load balance across available
workers is one of the key benefits of
using a broker you know much like you
would use a load balancer on a front end
like in genix to talk to multiple
backend servers you would use a Q and
you could have multiple consumers on
that que to load balance and scale up
you you can even set scaling rules to
say hey run more instances of the
container if there's more messages in
the queue and you can do things like
that with Kafka as well but Kafka is
really more so just about Pub sub and
not about that dispatch type processing
of consuming from the front of the queue
and then you know either writing to
other cues or producing other events and
all of that type stuff so great and I
think as we continue in the episode it
will become more clear specifically what
a message bus is for and the use cases
that it's more catered to before we dive
into that though and talk a little bit
more in detail what are some use cases
before we Dive In Too Deep where a
message bus just might not make sense
again we're going back to that why do I
just want to distribute if I don't need
to if you have like a read heavy
application that is just reading data
say you're you know doing a bunch of
munging on stuff and let's say you have
a pricing service you know and the
pricing service does nothing but grind
over cataloges process contract rules
and output a bunch of tables that say
what the price is that's something where
you're going to want low response time
high availability and you're going to
want to scale it out many times a case
like that you might just use a Pure API
against a redis cache or an inmemory
database that you want the absolute
least amount of latency possible so
that's a case where you might not want
to use a message bus for that there are
plenty of cases where you know it's a
closed system or it's a processing and
you know the events may be produced
elsewhere you know ETL type things I
don't really think that's a case where
you would want events but the reality is
is because of the benefits of
asynchronous processing and I know one
of the other things we need to talk
about is like message persistence and
durability you you might want to use
this because you get that durable
asynchronous processing so those are
things that we probably want to cover as
well but you know cases where you just
you know you're never going to scale out
you know you're never going to need to
produce or consume events from other
systems you know the reality is is there
are always cases where you might need to
you know take that high read scenario
that we just discussed if the high read
system has an in-memory cache and the
backend database is updated somehow you
have to notify all those SC bailed out
workers that the cache was just
refreshed and to dump everything from in
memory okay well how do you do that do
you call the database and check a flag
to see last update and if it's there do
it or do you just push an event over the
message bus so that it then dumps its in
memory caches and all calls go back to
the database at that point so it's going
to depend upon cost and complexity and
what you need but you may not want the
message bus to be part of that execution
path if the absolute lowest latency is
needed great and of course we always end
up mentioning at least one of the two
hard problems in computer science you
just hearkened to cash invalidation
which is one of them and of course then
there's naming things and off by One
problems but moving on from that you had
a great segue there for a second I want
to go back you mentioned persistence and
durability and the importance of talking
about those in the space of a message
bus so I think most listeners know what
they are but just briefly what is
persistence and what is durability and
kind of what's the difference between
those Concepts and then why do they
matter in the context of message buses
but also in the just in systems design
in general
so yeah so when you think about an HTTP
request coming into your system they're
calling an API and you're doing
something and if that HTTP connection is
broken or if that inflight controller
crashes or that process crashes it's
gone I mean you're cutting the HTTP
connection they're getting a 500 error
from the load balancer and then they
basically have to call the API again
with a message bus and using a message
broker as the ones we've mentioned they
all support durable messaging and what I
mean by durable is when a message is
published it is acknowledged and the
task completes knowing that that message
is reliably written to dis on the broker
so that it is not going to be lost so if
you have an API and that API submits an
order and that order is written to a
queue that order is then saved in that
que it's durable and the consumer of
that message is going to be able to
receive it regardless of what happens in
that API call you know if the caller
disconnects or if there's a network
failure or anything like that that order
has been reliably captured in that queue
you know with HTTP if I was calling into
my API and then I was making an API call
to the order system like directly to an
Erp to create an order on you know say
sap or something like that and it takes
8 nine 10 seconds if you're lucky and
you don't really have a deterministic
outcome from that if something crashes
by writing it to a q i get that
durability and I know that I can process
that message the other benefit of that
is it's DEC coupled you know if you
think about it it's that loose coupling
between the two cars of the train that
means that if the backend processing of
orders slows down we're still able to
accept new orders into that queue you
know if we're receiving you know a big
burst because you know we just had a
halftime ad during the Super Bowl and
it's like hey punch in this code to get
your free whatchacallit all of those
incoming messages could be written to
the queue and we could process those as
we have the system capacity to do so and
they won't be lost because they are in
that Q so it's a great way to handle
bursts of traffic without overloading
your backend system or your database
that might have a three or 4 second
process to do some sort of order
validification or adjudication or
talking to the warehouse system or any
of those type of interactions that's
great so effectively once I get a
message on the bus so to speak now
basically it's in a database and there
are some guarantees about how that's
going to be persisted and then
eventually delivered and then when it's
processed there's also guarantees about
how will be removed from the queue with
the knowledge that it has been received
by whoever needed to receive that
message exactly and it happens on the
consumer side too when I consume a
message from a queue I'm getting a lock
on that message and say you know I have
five minutes to process it and so I'm
going to do a few things and if it's
going to take me a little longer it'll
renew that lock and it does these things
under the covers for you these aren't
things you have to do explicitly but if
the process crashes that message is
still on the Queue and when that lock
times out it's going to redeliver that
to a consumer once again and so that
consumer can say hey now I'm going to
process it and there are counters and
Fields in there where it can look and
say hey I've tried this 10 times and I
keep crashing the process maybe I should
take this poison pill and put it
somewhere else because this is clearly a
special case that's causing a system
issue and so then mass transit will move
it to like an error cue or a dead letter
cue to say hey these need to be handled
some other way because they keep taking
down the system well and there's a great
transition cuz you just said mass
transit instead of message bus so let's
talk about that we've been talking about
message buses which is a good
foundational you know topic to explore
here but now let's talk about mass
transit what is it and how does it
relate to the conversation so far so
mass transit is an open- Source message
bus it's a distributed application
framework because it's more than just a
message bus it provides an abstraction
that sits on top of rabbit mq Azure
service bus Amazon sqs and active mq and
it provides publish And subscribe
semantics as well as direct send and in
even request response semantics for
different message patterns so there's a
number of different message patterns I
just described three there's a few more
but the abstraction provided by mass
transit makes it very easy to write your
applications using again I've made a
mention of you know asp.net controller
and action relationship before we went
to minimal API obviously but you know
because now everybody wants to do that
but it's very much a way to say hey I
have a consumer which is just a class I
want to consume this message type which
is just implementing an interface or I
want to consume these three message
types which is just implementing three
interfaces of the same one with just
different message types and then I get a
consume method and these things you know
mass transit takes care of all the
wiring it does things like the
serialization the writing and reading of
messages to the transport whether it's
you know any of the mentioned Brokers it
deals with all of the configuration mass
transit has this concept of framework
defined infrastructure so you create
consumers and message types and any of
the different types of consumer consum
mass transit supports and then mass
transit will then go out and create the
appropriate topics on Azure service bus
or cues or rabit mq exchanges or any of
the underlying message broker
infrastructure components such that you
don't have to worry about that so when
you think about migrations from like
Entity framework and how you go code
first and you create a class and you
create a map and then it goes out and
creates a database table for you mass
transit does the same thing it's
framework defined it says okay well
based on on what you're consuming and
producing I'm going to go create these
topics I'm going to create these cues
I'm going to set all this up for you and
make sure it's wired up correctly so
those are just some of the things that
mass transit provides but it makes it
easy to say I want to write my code
maybe I want to test it locally on
rabbit mq but I want to deploy it in
production in Azure service bus for our
Azure customers and maybe in Amazon for
our Amazon AWS customers so gives you
some portability across all those
different underlying Brokers yeah that's
great and sounds like it's developer
focused as well with the fact that you
don't have to spend a bunch of time
learning how to set up the Brokers or
the exchanges and Q or whatever there is
in the underlying broker technology
that's kind of taken care of for you
which is nice I'm glad you said that
because when we first started mass
transit Drew sers and I I guess it was
what 16 17 however many years ago our
key Focus was being developer first you
know and not spending too much time you
know thinking about writing things and
other languages or 4gls or any of that
you know if you're writing in C you're
right at home with mass transit because
you don't have to learn a bunch of other
languages so are there any use cases
before we get into more of these
patterns you know we're going to talk
about event driven systems and different
patterns of distributed architecture and
things of this nature but are there use
cases for simpler environments as well
like if someone's building an on-prem
system or a monolithic architecture
where they might introduce something
like mass transit like can I add it to
an existing system do I have to start
from scratch like how can this fit in
say a Brownfield application or a more
Classic on premer monolithic environment
there's a number of options there and a
lot of customers do that you know
customers that I've worked with through
you know providing support for mass
transit a lot of customers and this is a
really solid use case that they do a lot
is believe it or not there's a lot of
companies that have a lot of NET
Framework 472 or you know any of the old
you know traditional framework but you
know they have teams and their
developers are like we need to be
building everything with net 8 now so
they're like how it's going to be nine
in a week by the time this show drops so
yeah yeah yeah well nine is out now but
eight is LTS if you're doing six you're
way behind the times cuz six is end of
life already which freaks some people
out but it's like they were upfront
about it they were but you have these
teams that want to build modern you know
net core applications and they want to
you know have fun with all that but
they've got this existing monolith so a
lot of the times I see customers they'll
use mass transit to just add event
producers to their existing monolithic
code and so then they'll write that out
to like rabbit mq on Prem because you
can run Rabbit mq anywhere it just runs
anywhere and what they'll do is then
they'll create their additional
sidebyside services that are running
over in you know they might be running
in containers or a lot of them might
just be running as Windows Services you
know using the net generic host and
they'll make those run and process
messages from that same message broker
using a couple of you know they might
have like a shared message contract
library and say these are the events
that are produced from the monolith in
quotes and the new microservices over
here are then processing those events
and talking to our other systems or you
know in one case we had a customer that
they were actually building software on
a fairly large platform written in a
language that we don't want to talk
about too much but they needed to be
able to call external apis with ooth
validation and their monolith had no
capabilities to do that so what they did
is they actually produced commands out
of their monolithic application writing
to the message broker and then their
microservices built in net 6 at the time
would then get those requests messages
make the actual HTP calls with all the
ooth tokens and everything write the
responses back onto another rabbit mq
which would then be picked up by the
monolith and to the monolith it was just
an RPC call which it was familiar with
because that's how most monoliths are
written and it just you know it took a
little bit more time because it was
going out of process and talking to
another third party service but it met
their needs and was well within their
capacity requirements so it gave them
that ability to kind of build new
technologies into their existing
monolith without having to dis rupt the
monolith or do the oh let's try to
migrate the whole thing to net 8 yeah
that's never going to go well or rewrite
the whole thing but let's not go there
yeah that's even worse we could do a
whole show on that I'm sure you have yes
but I avoid it now so again moving on
great Segway there actually you started
talking about Concepts that fit firmly
in the camp of event-driven architecture
and you know you talked a little bit
about how for existing maybe monolithic
system or something like that that you
can use a tool like mass transit to
support event- driven architecture what
are some other aspects of that that you
can share when we talk about you know
robustness or scaling or retry how do
those play into this and give us some
concrete examples of where you benefit
from using a framework like mass transit
for those sorts of Concepts yeah so when
you talk about the capabilities provided
by the framework and by you know the
framework being mass transit there are a
number of different things that you can
do you mentioned like robustness and
scaling and retry you know when you're
reading from a queue you automatically
get this you know multiple consumers on
the Q scaling so you're able to scale up
and manage that but as far as like
robustness things like if you do have a
system failure such as a downstream
system that API you're calling to
validate the price might be down you
know they might be having an outage or
someone you know ran a back ho through
your fiber connection at the data center
you know it doesn't happen much now with
stuff in the cloud but when you're
talking on Prem it happens all the time
especially if you have facilities all
across the us so you know the internet
goes out so in those scenarios you want
to be able to do things like okay well I
need to stop processing from the queue
or I need to retry because maybe it was
just a transient Spike maybe it was just
one of those weird 500s that you know or
maybe I exceeded my rate limit so mass
transit has a lot of what we refer to as
middleware that allows you to do things
like setup retries setup kill switches
which I think a lot of people call it a
circuit breaker but essentially saying
hey I've tried to call five times and
it's not responding I'm going to stop
for a little bit and wait and you know
give the system a chance to settle and
then go back and come back in you know a
couple minutes and try to start
processing again versus just throwing
everything into an error CU and saying
it's not processible so those type of
things give you some benefit there you
know I've just mentioned error que if
messages are completely unprocessable
and you've specified you know retry 10
times and if you get this error this is
actually bad you have some granularity
in how you specify things like retry
handling you know rate limiting of
saying hey I can only call you know some
of my customers use Shopify and it's
like you can only call Shopify a 100
times a second if you call it more than
that you start getting weird errors so
they put rate limits on their consumers
that are actually updating their
inventory price or creating orders in
the Shopify system so that they don't
overflow the API and cause weird
Downstream system errors because when
you're dealing with a lot of these
external providers especially like a
Shopify or a stripe or any of the
payment providers it isn't a one-way
conversation you know when you talk
about a distributed system and building
in an event driven way you also have
this concept of you know if I call
Shopify and create an order I'm going to
get a web hook call back that's going to
be like oh I have an order created or
that order was processed or that order
change State handling those web hooks
that is a use case where using a message
bus is 100% the way you should be doing
it because if you're letting an web hook
call go straight into your database you
know at the behest of whatever you know
that provider is doing you know you
could miss it because if you fail to
process it you might not get it ever
again so all of the backend like Shopify
web hook handlers and these other
systems that hit you up when you know
you receive money like through stripe or
whatever all of those in the cases of
the customers that I've worked with are
getting those and writing those to Q's
so that they can then process those you
know at their own Leisure using a
variety of the different capabilities of
the system what are some common
challenges you've seen when people want
to adopt an event-driven approach to
their systems when these concepts are
new to them you know a lot of people
especially when they come from like the
API samples or you know a lot of people
learn from samples they're like most of
the questions I get through the support
form we like how do I do this is there a
sample of this and you can tell that
that person literally just got a
requirement dropped into their Jura
bucket and they're
like okay so I'm just going to cut and
paste this to Chris and say do you have
one of these because I just want that so
this was msdn back when we were when we
were younger and now it's been stack
Overflow who knows what it's now it's
chat GPT now it's chat GPT fortunately
and I've the amount of chat GPT code
I've been submitted from a support
request is hilarious cuz I can almost
recognize it now uhhuh cuz that has my
variable names in
it a lot of people come from this
transaction script mindset you know they
call my APN I'm going to do some things
right now and then I'm going to be done
and a lot of it comes from just the
request response mentality you know you
think about an API request you get a
request you do some things and you
respond so it's how a lot of people
think and mass transit supports that
very well I mean it has the capabilities
to do it and it provides a lot of cool
capabilities to make that actually even
better than it is with just like an API
controller and we'll get into that when
we start talking about like sagas and
state machines and things like that but
to go back to kind of the question you
know the challenges is it's like it's
getting around the mindset of you know
what is synchronous and what is
asynchronous and when I say synchronous
I also mean like async await if you're
using a wait it's synchronous if you're
waiting for something and that's fine
you could do an await and I mean it
really increases the scalability of your
application but the difference of async
processing through durable messaging is
you may not need to await you can just
guarantee that that fire and forget
you've said something needs to happen
and it will happen but you don't need to
wait for it to happen so you can you
know respond to that API and get your
latency down you know a few seconds you
know it's thinking about that the other
challenge we discussed earlier is that
debugging experience you can't just F10
through it and see every line of code
execute and complete you know so that's
kind of a shift believe it or not one of
the biggest challenges or impediments is
getting Buy in from leadership you know
the people in the team they watch one of
the videos on YouTube from any of the
influencers in the or they listen to
software engineering radio or they
listen to this and they think I have a
shiny new Hammer I going to go pound
some nails with this thing and
everything's in nail now of course of
course it is and so then their
leadership comes in and they're like
yeah but we really don't have the
capacity to stand up rabit mq or we
don't have that and you know the nice
thing is that with mass transit I've now
the kibos on that statement because now
if you're using SQL Server postgress you
can use those as a transport mass
transit has a built-in SQL transport
where you can just create and do all you
know the same capabilities You' get from
rabbit mq even beyond that are available
by using SQL as a transport with just
mass transit out of the box so now they
can't argue about separate
infrastructure having to be set up so
now it's just a question of can you
sneak it in without leadership finding
out not that I would recommend that well
you shouldn't ask for permission to do
the right thing but you know forgiveness
permission you know anybody who's
married knows how that works could be a
whole episode but we'll move on exactly
let's dive a little bit more into a few
topics related to Performance and
operations around mass transit so I'm
sure it depends somewhat on the
transport but give us a sense of how
many messages and what amount of time
can mass transit handle in common
scenarios I get that question a lot
people are like what's my throughput you
know how can I get that and like for
producing durable messages to Rabbit mq
I can do 2 thousands a second I mean
like 8 10 12,000 messages a second so
it's it's really going to depend upon
how big of a broker you provision with
Azure service bus I created like an M4
you know it was like $600 an hour or
something it was ridiculous but I ran it
long enough to run the Benchmark it
might have been per day but I was able
to get around four to 6,000 messages a
second produced and consumed through
Azure service bus using that level of
configuration so it's it's whatever
you're willing to in best in it from the
underlying infrastructure because the
broker is the bottleneck and so you know
it really depends and it depends upon
how you're using it how many cues things
like that you know mass transit
encourages the use of many cues so you
don't have you know two people
requesting two separate Services waiting
in the same line you know it's not
doesn't have to be the DMV you can
actually fan out and you know have
separate cues but the scalability of the
broker is the real thing what I found at
least in most applications is people
think they have a lot of throughput and
then they realize they don't because
their database might take 10 to 12
milliseconds to do each operation which
if you do the math that's 100 a second
and you know being able to do more than
a thousand messages a second with like
the SQL transport that I mentioned is
more than enough for most customers you
know so it makes it applicable but there
are people doing some very very high
volume distributed system stuff with
rabbit mq to the point where they even
don't even need message durability they
turn it off and I've seen 16 20 24,000
messages a second flying through Rabbit
mq Without You know any real major
issues there so so we mentioned before
during the show there's challenges with
distributed systems because it's hard to
just get a debugger going on on these
multiple distributed systems which leads
into some topics that are I think Hot
Topics in our industry today related to
monitoring and observability so speak a
little bit to how mass transit helps
support those for sure you know Mass
transits on version 8 which came out I
want to say like 18 months ago it's
getting on 2 years but the main
capability brought in there was kind of
the standard.net observability using
open Telemetry so when you are
processing messages from the time that
API call hits in all the way through all
your message consumers sagas scheduled
messages everything you're able to see
that complete Trace in like an open
tretry dashboard such as application
insights or even if it's just using kind
of the some of the Freer ones I know din
trce has support for it as well but the
ability to visualize and see that
complete trace of every message through
the system has really I think opened up
the observability of distributed systems
and made them a bit easier to understand
mass transit actually uses open
Telemetry internally for some things
like checking to see if something is
done like in the testing framework mass
transit has a robust testing framework
and it makes it easy to unit test your
consumers your sagas you know produce
events for them and like stimulate them
to do things and do so using an inmemory
analogy of a transport I wrote an
in-memory inter implementation of rabbit
mq so that you could test like
publishing consuming load balancing all
of that type stuff and you're able to
test your consumers with that it's how I
recommend people test things because if
you're testing just your consumer for
its inputs and outputs you're truly unit
testing you know M you can also fully
set up a you know it's it's fully
container based you can figure it the
same way you know you have a service
collection you add mass transit test
harness and you can just test your
consumers as they are with their
dependencies it's also really easy to
set up like dummies or test doubles to
say hey if this message is produced
produce this one in response so you can
like simulate other parts of the system
that a consumer might be dependent upon
and it also works with the asp.net web
application Factory I think it's their
test application framework that they
have for asp.net where it actually
stands up your apis in kind of a test
host mass transit works with that as
well so if you add the test harness
it'll replace you know say your Azure
service bus configuration with an
in-memory one that allows you to like
test your API controllers or your map
gets map posts all that kind of minimal
API stuff directly with interactions
with mass transit consumers so it's
really robust and it makes it I think
really easy to test and you can even in
your tests output like a call graph of
the open Telemetry taste to see what
happened and where the time spans were
of everything so that's great that
visualization really helps yeah yeah
it's when I look at it and I see
something that looks like it shouldn't
be there it's like oh yeah no wonder
it's taking 12 seconds because it hung
up on something well and something else
too speaking of debugging and
troubleshooting you mentioned before if
a message maybe you try it 10 times and
then eventually you put it in you know a
dead letter cue which we'll put notes in
in links in the show notes for listeners
to go learn about these things but
effectively now I imagine what you can
do is you can go grab that message and
maybe redeliver it in a test environment
and get the bug to show up and then you
can fix it deploy the fixed code and
then publish the message back to the q
and fix the bug and nobody maybe the
customer never even knows the difference
I mean you should be in advertising I
mean oh sorry I'm not trying to be such
an advocate I'm just saying like it
seems like but no that's exactly
something you could do right which you
couldn't do in a request response
scenario no I mean we used to do that
all the time like try to catch we would
like write out to a log file the input
parameters of an API call to try to
reproduce What the customer was doing or
dump their Json payload to dis and a
directory now you have the message yeah
it's we're going to talk about security
next by the way oh
no right but yeah being able to take
that message out of the error que try it
in a non-prod environment get the bug
fix out there and then just move those
messages from the error queue back into
the queue for reprocessing yeah customer
wouldn't have to be any of the wiser it
just gets fixed so speaking of security
are there any security related issues to
consider either things that are
potentially made simpler or easier or
things that are challenging in this kind
of you know a mass transit framework
environment that people should be aware
of you know I've had to help customers
fill out a number of different security
audits for their isrm teams their risk
management teams I think the from an
architectural guidance perspective
messaging should stay within the domain
and if you have multiple domains such as
like warehousing and billing and
auditing and ordering and all of those
different domains be careful what
messages are public or shared across
those domains and which ones are in an
internal domain you know mass transit
has a multibus feature where you can
connect a m multiple Brokers and for
large scale systems I've actually seen
customers have like a rabbit mq per
vertical you know like accounting might
have their own rabbit mq and warehousing
may have their own rabbit mq and each
Warehouse might have their own rabbit mq
on PR running in a warehouse and then
there's an overall Azure service bus on
top of that and with mass transit you
can connect to multiple buses and you
can say okay well these are the events
that are across the whole application
landscape and these are the ones that
are local to say accounting and so when
you think about it as like public or
external events or internal events and
that type of encapsulation really helps
keep the security folks happy because
then it's very clear what you're
communicating outside of your domain but
one thing that I definitely don't
recommend or should I say highly
discourage is people saying oh well
messaging is so great we love it so much
let's make our customers call us through
Azure service bus instead of an API you
know a apis are great because they have
things like authentication and they work
well with your off providers like you
know know OCTA or azero or you know
actor directory there's reasons people
use apis with all of these layers of
security because they're easy to audit
and Trace and control access to message
Brokers are a little more Wild West in
that once you're in the message broker
things like you know role-based access
control and stuff get very weird and and
they just don't make sense in messaging
and I see a lot of people try to apply
these to it you know so what I generally
recommend is from to keep your security
folks happy and using the standard tools
that they're familiar with with stick to
apis for your external interactions with
outside third parties or customers and
then in those apis produce or consume
those messages and get those out because
you're G to you're going to pass a lot
of security audits that way I mean
message Brokers if you get down to like
message level signing and authentication
and everything you're bringing a lot of
complexity and robustness and details
you know if you think about the onion
architecture or kind of the concept of
core domain from the domain driven
design book by Eric Evans that core
domain should be your business domain
and those external things like ooth 2 or
open ID connect or those things that
change every 5 to 10 years in our
industry should be at the very outside
of your architecture and shouldn't make
its way into the core domain and
Eventing is because of the way people
are architecting systems and with
asynchronous processing and durable
Eventing in mind it's a fact of life
that that type of event bus architecture
is part of your core domain at this
point let's talk about some patterns
that Frameworks like mass transit
support and starting with just from a
high level talk a little bit we don't
need to get into too many details about
what they are there's other episodes or
people can look online but let's talk
about how mass transit supports and
relates to approaches like event
sourcing and cqrs which is command query
responsibility segregation ah yes cqrs
and event sourcing two of my favorite
words mass transit is not an event
sourcing framework so I'll say that
upfront there are some of those out
there but in an Event Source system you
may be able to produce events from those
that would be consumed by mass transit
and could be used by number of the
capabilities in the framework to store
things like you would do in a cqrs
system so command query responsibility
segregation you know the separation of
reads from rights is really what I just
simplify it down to you know mass
transit it's what it was built for I
mean your commands are coming in they're
validated commands they're
99.9% guaranteed to succeed you're
writing those commands to a queue and
you're processing those with your
consumers or you know other messaging
patterns that you might use to get those
done the events produced by consuming
those commands are then used to populate
things like your read stores or your
view caches or any of those things that
are providing that query response back
to the customer through those apis you
know you may be using events to update a
reddest database of order status so that
when an API comes in you just hit redus
and say hey what's the current order
status now mass transit has some better
capabilities for that I think that gets
you more up-to-date information without
having to maintain a separate cache and
we can go into those in the pattern
section but the intent being you know if
you're building a CQ QRS system you're
more than likely going to use a message
bus you know whether it's end service
bus mass transit Rebus brighter command
you know there's a number of different
Frameworks that are out there I have a
favorite but some would say I'm
biased well you mentioned patterns and
one of the patterns that comes up a lot
in this context is sagas so what are
they and what can they be used for and
give listener some specific real world
examples if you can I will so Saga
messaging pattern and when I talk about
in this context I'm really talking about
a a saga that maintains state so when
you think about a message consumer a
message consumer consumes a message does
something and then it's done it doesn't
have any state they are stateless now if
you write a consumer that goes and
updates a row in a database well you're
kind of manipulating state with a
consumer but the consumer itself doesn't
maintain State sagas are stateful and
within mass transit the best way to
create sagas is by defining a state
machine so you know something happens
that initially creat an instance of that
state and the state machine defines the
behavior of events and how they interact
with that state over time so you know
when we talk about an order you know
when an order is submitted that order
submitted event might initiate a saga
you know tied to that order ID and then
as subsequent events in the system
happen those events can be correlated
back to that same order such as you know
order payment approved you know order
fulfilled order shipped all of those
type of events in the system could be
correlated back to that order and update
the state on that Saga so if the end
user wants to get a status of their
order they may produce a order status
requested event which could be consumed
by The Saga and then the Saga could then
respond back because sagas can
participate in request response respond
with that state back to the API caller
therefore eliminating the need for a
read store because the state of the
order is right there in that Saga and
it's just observing those events you
know when you think about terms there's
two terms orchestration and choreography
when you think about orchestrating a
process such as an order process sagas
are the orchestrator for like an order
you know when the order is submitted the
Saga could then send off events to say
hey I need to go validate that order I
need to go you know check payment I need
to go see if they still have a valid
customer account if it's a controlled
item maybe they need to have
authorization to purchase are they
authorized to buy and then they might
have custom pricing too you know the
order might be like hey you know I know
you quoted me pricing on the site but if
they're a gold customer they might get
you know 10% off so we might do some
price adjustments based on that order
anything that we would want to do with
that and that's what sagas are meant to
do they're meant to orchestrate that
that process the state machine syntax
makes it very easy to think of state and
behavior separately such that you know
when this happens if I'm in this state I
want to do this thing you know and they
can be as simple as complex as they need
to be to meet the business requirement
but it gives you that nice stateful
consumer behavior that you might
otherwise get if you were to have a
consumer that would say oh well I want
to consume an order processed message
I'm going to go out to the database I'm
going to load the order I'm going to
check if it's in a certain State I mean
that's what sagas really are meant to
replace is those nouns in our system
that need to have something done to them
okay so they can help you manage a
multi-step process effectively for sure
okay that's great and speaking of
multi-step processes there's a couple
other patterns that it talks about on
the the mass transit documentation
transactions and outbox let's kind of
layer those in and let's talk about how
you know transactions we all know
they're tricky in a distributed system
and when I say transaction I don't
necessarily mean a database transaction
I I mean a business transaction you know
I think we kind of got this a little bit
with sagas but maybe talk a little bit
about more about how mass transit can
help with transactional consistency in
business processes and how things like
outbox can help with that for sure so
when we talk about state state has to be
S stored somewhere and so Saga state can
be persisted in a number of different
places I mean SQL Server
postgress you know aure Cosmos I mean
there's yeah mongodb there's a ton of
persistence providers for mass transit
to be able to store that Saga State and
handle the Locking on it because one of
the things that I didn't mention about
sagas but it's worth mentioning they
lock that state so only one message is
being processed by that state machine
for that particular State instance at a
time and if there's a optimistic or
pessimistic concurrency depending upon
the transport it will say oh well I did
this work and I went to finish but I
couldn't because someone else finished
before me you know that optimistic
concurrency so that's where we would
want to bring in something like an
outbox and mass transit has a
transactional outbox or just an inmemory
outbox depending upon what your needs
are to be able to say okay well I'm
going to process this and if everything
goes well the events that were produced
by that state machine are going to be
then sent to the broker because if you
think about it if I was to process
optimistically and say okay well I do
these things I publish these events to
the broker and now I'm going to go save
this and oh I got a concurrency conflict
because some other process was
processing a message for that same state
instance now I've got like events
floating out the system that may or may
not have happened or may have been
duplicated so the outbox eliminates that
it basically makes that transactional
commit of that Saga therefore result in
the messages being produced once versus
you know false messages being produced
through the system so it helps increase
that you know transaction ability of
State machine now the outbox actually
has two different modes that's the
consumer Saga outbox the bus outbox
actually is you know we talked about how
to produce messages well you may have an
old school process that just talks to a
database inserts some rows in a DB
context and then says save changes async
and if it works you want to produce an
event but with the bus out boox you can
actually produce that event within that
same transaction and this time we are
talking about a database transaction
such that when you call Save changes
async only if that transaction is
successful will those messages actually
be written to the database which then
get replayed back up to the broker so
that's another way that the outbox
pattern kind of comes in there and it's
all built in you just configure it it
just works it works for mongodb or
Entity framework okay so basically you
can have message publication participate
in a database transaction if I
understood you correctly yep 100% that's
what it's for okay that's great let's
talk about another pattern job consumers
what are they and when should they be
used so this is probably my favorite new
feature of mass transit it's been around
for a while you know we originally
called it turnout and it used to be
because you know you've got a consumer
but that consumer is going to go out and
calculate the infinity number of pi or
some ridiculously huge compute thing you
know it's going to convert an EG 4 video
to a QuickTime video you know something
it's gonna train a new llm yes exactly
it's G to train a new LM and it's going
to take a week to do it how many gpus
anyway yes yeah exactly and I mean
people do use them with gpus but that's
they just kind of a funny part so so
they had a couple of names early on you
know we used to use them processing big
import files but they started being
called job consumers with version 8 or I
don't know when but with version 8.3 we
really took it to the next level because
I wanted to really make it possible to
do job processing with just mass transit
you know and so you know job consumers
it's like a regular consumer it has a
different interface but it doesn't run
you know we mentioned that the broker
keeps the message locked it doesn't run
while the mess message is locked the job
consumer engine the job service that's
part of mass transit which uses believe
it or not three Saga State machines to
manage every job through the system so
it's just using mass transit handles the
scheduling and execution of job
consumers in the system and they run
without a message lock so they're just
running on a machine somewhere and it as
it completes and they can report
progress they can report they can save
State I mean they can do all the things
that you would really want to do with
like a long running job they can run and
do that
and mass transit is going to keep track
of that it's going to control like the
concurrency of it and now with 8.3 you
can actually schedule them and you can
schedule recurring ones so like all the
things that we used to grab like
hangfire or quartz to do in our systems
or just or a console app console app
with an event script with a schedu task
yes programming sins of our past yes
yeah exactly all those things that we've
like man it would sure be nice to do
this and I mean I would say that Drew
sers was one of the big pushers on this
cuz he was like dude when are you going
to get this done for me and it's like
what do I work for free and then I
realize that I do apparently right open
source yeah yeah so I put all this stuff
in there and now I mean it's super
compelling you can create recurring jobs
that run using just a Chon expression
and that math Works itself out and it'll
run like every hour on the hour and do
its thing and it runs with the same
semantics as a consumer that's great and
you don't need an external thing like
quartz or or anything anymore because as
because most Brokers can schedule
messages so like as service bus sqs now
sqs is limited cuz it's like to 12 hours
which is a little weird but even my SQL
transport now I mean with my SQL
transport you can build a complete job
system with postgress or SQL Server I
mean no external dependency you said my
SQL you just mean SQL transport my SQL
trans not my SQL the database your no it
does not support my SQL it
supports yes SQL transport sorry you
said my SQL I want to clarify there one
more thing on job consumers so just just
to clarify to make sure I understand you
mentioned that they're not locking in
other words typically when a consumer is
processing a message from the broker
there's a lock placed on that for as
long as the consumer is processing the
message until it can acknowledge that
it's completed processing with a job
consumer you're not holding on to that
message this allows you to process
something that might take longer than
the amount of time that you have to
process that message from a locked
message from a broker am I getting that
right exactly that's 100% correct in
fact the Locking is actually handled by
the three state machines that manage
every job
okay great so mass transit using itself
to make itself better yeah that's cool
it's kind of meta but that's that's cool
what about routing slips what are they
and what can they be used for and maybe
some specific examples again where
they're useful for sure so you know we
talked briefly about transactions and
how transactions are tricky in a
distributed system you know the the
canonical example of this is the travel
reservation system where I need to book
a hotel car and a flight you know all in
the same thing and if any one of those
fails I need to roll that back and go
back to the user and give them
alternative choices because you know if
my flight's not available obviously the
hotel is not going to do me any good so
routing slips are a way to compose so
remember we talked briefly earlier about
orchestration and choreography sagas are
orchestration routing slips or
choreography so routing slips let you
add a series of activities that run and
complete or not complete as a single
kind of transaction now that's the
textbook definition but it doesn't
always work out that way people do crazy
things when you create software for them
to do stuff but the intent is that
you're able to execute a series of
activities and if an activity throws an
exception and fails any previous
activity that completed is allowed the
opportunity to compensate itself so when
you think about compensating
transactions you know I booked my flight
I have a flight reservation ID number
which if you want to go into how that
really works we can but it's a lot like
the ATM you commit to buying a flight
and then you adjudicate it back in when
you actually pay for the flight but you
commit to buying a flight and you get a
number then you go book your hotel and
you get a reservation number and then
you go book a car and you get another
reservation number no money's changed
hands at this point if all three of
those things succeed the routing slip
completes and then your process is able
to go on and use those notifications to
then continue doing whatever it needs to
do let's say the car is not available so
it throws an exception and says hey I
couldn't book the car it's not available
well as it goes back through the
itinerary of the routing slip it says
hey well these two things things
previously completed I'm going to give
each of those activities an opportunity
to compensate itself and then produce an
overall event that says hey this routing
slip failed as a whole and so it that
compensation will go back to the hotel
and say hey we had a problem cancel this
reservation number and it says yeah okay
no problem we do this every day and then
it goes back to the airline and says
okay those seats are available again
we'll pull it back out and all of that
rolls back so that's what routing slips
are for they work similar to Consumers
it's just they have a different
interface they have inputs and and then
they have a log file that they can write
which that log is then stored in the
routing slip so the reason it's called a
routing slip is with a saga you have a
central point of control that's always
talking to a database with a routing
slip the network is used to capture that
state so the routing slip message itself
on the broker also includes all of the
state it has a variables collection
which is like a key value dictionary
that can keep track of everything that's
happened and provides a shared memory
space for all of the activities in that
ring slip that sounds like the message
is the application pattern I've heard
before I'm familiar with that one but
yeah like everything is carried in the
message so that there is no Central
thing that everybody has to check in
with yeah so would you ever combine a
saga and a routing slip together to
solve that make it complex but then
again are there situations where it
makes sense to combine some
orchestration with some choreography in
some scenarios I would say 80% of the
time it works every time meaning
individually SE like just a saga or just
a r both 80% of the time you're going to
use both oh you are going to use both
yeah okay now explain why well because
you may have an order that is a noun in
your system but you may need to
communicate with five systems to do some
processing step of that order by
building that routing slip and running
that you're eliminating the need to put
all that complexity into your Saga
because if you think about it from an
orchestration tell a to do something
okay a did it tell B to do something
okay B did it whereas if I can say okay
I Need A B C D and E to do their things
and then when it's all done let me know
I can do that as a separate
choreographed set of activities that
then I get the disposition of back in
the Saga to determine what to do next so
it's a matter of compartmentalizing
complexity to avoid having a massive
Saga State machine with you know 342
States and you know all of the
complexity that goes with that it allows
you to compartmentalize that behavior
and I would imagine as well you can do
things like set timeouts and say this
step you know this particular consum
the orchestrator might say I'm going to
you know do the a the B and the C in
parallel with a routing slip to kind of
extend this example so to make it more
concrete maybe I want to check inventory
check your payments and get a shipping
provider so something like this and I
want to use a routing slip to do those
three things but the orchestrator might
say but that all needs to happen within
the next six hours or else I'm going to
do something else and I imagine there's
ways I can configure that so I could
sort of pick up the pieces if something
just takes a long time to respond and I
don't actually get an error yeah yeah so
Saga State machines have the ability to
schedule events to themselves so you can
say hey I have a Time window of 60
Minutes in which case I have to escalate
this order if all of the processes
Downstream haven't completed yet let's
talk a little bit about interop what if
somebody's interop because I know mass
transit as you've described it works in
the net ecosystem and so what if I've
got to talk to something that's written
in Java or that's written in some other
language and maybe it's going to talk to
a message broker you imagine that's what
it's going to do you know how do I are
there things that I can do to interupt
better with those other systems with
something like mass transit yeah
definitely so I mean I think we've
reached a point in the universe where
Jason is the language of the wire I mean
pretty much not soap sorry shouldn't go
there there is still XML and soap out
there believe it or not but it's it's
becoming less frequent as people you
know start to update their systems and
Json is available or they go through you
know a middleware you know or a true
Enterprise service bus like a mu soft or
something that can translate XML to
Jason and all that stuff and it never
has the Fidelity you want but someone
paid money for it and so you got to use
it the interop is actually pretty easy
because a lot of people speak Jason you
know and mass transit has a number of
ways to be very liberable when it
accepts but very deliberate in what it
produces so you can accept any Json from
any source and to some point I think you
can try to do that with XML as well just
raw XML but that goes back to Newton
soft and pretty much everybody likes
system teex Json now not everybody I
know there's some Newton soft lovers out
there still but not the author so yeah
so with system Tech Jason I mean Jason
it's very easy to pull in pretty much
anything from any system and anything
mass transit produces is either going to
be just raw Json or it's wrapped Json
mass transit uses a message envelope by
default so it has a lot of headers and
stuff in it and provides a lot of Rich
data in addition to just the message
body but not everybody does that so it's
very easy to consume anything that's
Jason and you can do it mass transit has
the concept of a writer so you know when
I message what a real message broker is
you know we also talked about Kafka well
mass transit can consume events from
Kafka and event Hub by using a rider
which is a way to bring messages in
through topics in Kafka and it can also
produce events back out to topics in
Kafka but again that's that's very much
a consume and produce conversation
that's very different from like publish
And subscribe even though they say Pub
sub is a Kafka thing it's really just
you have multiple consumers on the topic
it's very different architecture in
kopka so bringing data in from other
systems is very easy a lot of the people
I know using kofka are using AV the
message format which is very different
from Jason but they use Avro because
it's binary and it's very tight and it's
very common and it works with any
language Mass transit's able to consume
those Arro messages from Kafka and bring
them into like a business domain that
might be using say rabbit mq or Azure
service bus internally where they might
just use Json internally so it can speak
different languages and you can even
specify different serialization types
per message type within mass transit so
it's kind of it's kind of flexible in
that way when you produce things out so
you can say hey when I publish this
event it needs to be raw Json because
the system consuming it doesn't know
your headers and then I think we touched
on it a little bit more but any other
thoughts on multibus like when would I
want to have you know multiple instances
of mass transit running to talk to
different Brokers or even maybe a
combination of the in-memory broker with
you know a backing broker like Azure
service bus or Rabbid mq you know when I
think of you know and I don't I hate
dropping names because they don't really
make sense and I don't know if they
actually use mass transit but when you
think about like the it's not even a
convenience store if you live in America
and you drive on any Highway you're
going to see $12 generals at every small
town along the way and when you think
about you probably have inore operations
and then you have corporate operations
that goes back to the kind of the
central office that's a case where if
your application is like running on a
register or a fulfillment system you
might want to use multibus to say
process stuff within the building like
using rabbit mq and then produce events
back out using Azure service bus using
multibus within the same application you
know because it lets you have multiple
bus instances all within service
collection which you know is pretty much
the standard dependency injection
container for net at this point that's
the main use case I see a mass transit
does have a mediator which if you're
familiar with mediator you know it's
it's an in-memory mediator
implementation that does not use a
broker or anything or even simulate one
it's a very synchronous way of calling
but it lets you use the same consumer
types with you know just just an
asynchronous call to the IM mediator I
scoped mediator interface and lets you
do that as well so it's not really a
multibus but it does allow you to do
kind of that I guess it's commonly
referred to as like the clean
architecture pattern where your API
calls through mediator through some
middleware to a consumer that then may
produce events to a broker so so what's
next for mass transit Chris what is next
job consumers was pretty huge that was a
big drop that was something I wanted to
get done you know the SQL transport is
obviously a pretty new thing you know
when I think of I think one of the other
things I really want to tackle and I've
got a branch for it is multi- tendency
you know mass transit being an
application framework that that defines
kind of how your event-based
applications are built I think another
piece of that is to provide kind of that
multi-tenant support because a lot of
people are building SAS apps with mass
transit and in many cases they just have
a message property or something that's
like a tenant ID but I want to take that
capability further to where when they
have like separate databases per tenant
or things like that you know and there's
there's a couple of commonly used like
multi- tendency Frameworks out there and
I'm just trying to look at what they
have and see what makes sense being able
to you know connect to even like a
broker per tenant because you know
multi-tenancy doesn't necessarily mean
you have a thousand tenants in a lot of
cases it's like well we have 10 you know
but they really got to be on their own
Brokers because you know legal you know
when you talk about security so you know
coming up with a way to do that where
you know how it would work to where they
would have a bus that they could access
that would be 10 and aware you know
that's something I think that would be
super valuable I don't have a lot of
customers that are actually asking for
that but you know just in general in the
community I think there's a desire out
there and it's one of those things that
I think would be clever to write so
that's something I mean I continue to
offer support and Consulting around mass
transit I mean it is kind of my
full-time gig so you know and I take
care you know customers that are support
customers actually prioritize the
backlog so the things they ask for first
get done first but you know mass transit
is still open source has a lot of
community contributions of things you
know someone just added message pack
serialization a few weeks ago so I was
kind of like oh I've never used it but
sure thanks that's great and we could do
a whole show on open source and inner
Source one more question on the idea of
multi tendency could that be an
opportunity as well to possibly
introduce some things around like
regionality like say you know I've got
Azure East Azure West and these maybe
use some tendency to determine message
delivery or or things or what resources
to use for whether it's data sovereignty
or jurisdictional requirements or things
like that is that something else that
you might consider including well I mean
when you talk about a tenant tenant's
just a way to differentiate and talk to
different message Brokers so your tenant
might be Gio right you know it might be
hey we're in Germany so because I have a
German tenant ID I need to select the
broker that's in a German data center
you know so it could certainly be used
for things like that I mean it's it's
really just a key to access some backend
thing so you know tenant is you know
kind of one of those things that could
be a lot of things well if people want
to get involved or learn more where can
they go Mast transit. is the main web
page from there you can get everywhere
we've got a Super Active Discord channel
the GitHub site mass transit you know is
the organization mass transit Mass
transit's the project there's
discussions on there you can go in and
kind of search and see what's out there
those are the main places that people
hang out I mean it's an active project
it's been around for over 15 years it's
used worldwide and if I look at my stats
in real time it's just like looking at
who's awake I can literally see what
part of the world is awake by looking
Sun never sets on the mass transit
Empire yes and unfortunately that means
if I'm awake and I'm on Discord people
are asking
questions I think some people are
shocked when I answer at like 10 pm on a
Saturday and I'm like hey you know I
just happen to see it there you go there
you go well you have nothing else to do
with your time so we appreciate exactly
well Chris thank you so much for joining
me on the show it's been great being
here it's been a fun conversation this
is Jeff dittle for software engineering
radio thanks so much for listening we
see you next
time thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by It
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for listening